<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majestie's gracious speech to the honorable House of Commons in the banquetting-house at White-hall, March I. 1662.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3069A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175746</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612070</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2786:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majestie's gracious speech to the honorable House of Commons in the banquetting-house at White-hall, March I. 1662.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p. : coat of arms.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by His Majestie's Printers ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>and re-printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno, 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Royal arms on t.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>The King's request to the Commons for the revenue to support the Crown.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Finance, Personal --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <p>His Majeſtie's GRACIOUS SPEECH To the Honorable HOUSE of COMMONS In the Banquetting-houſe at VVhite-hall, <hi>March</hi> 1. 1662.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by His MAjESTIE'S Printers; and Re-printed at <hi>Edinburgh, Anno,</hi> 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <head>His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Gracious Speech to the Honorable Houſe of Commons, at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> 
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 1. 1662.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding it neceſſary to ſay ſomewhat to you, I thought once of doing it by a Meſſage, which hath been the moſt uſual way; but when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that ſpeaking to you My Self, with that plainneſs and freedom I uſe to do, hath more of kindneſs in it, and with what affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you uſe to receive what I ſay to you; I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to deliver My Meſſage to you My Self, and and have therefore ſent for you hither, which hath been frequently done heretofore, though it be the firſt time I have done ſo.</p>
            <p>I do ſpeak My heart to you, when I tell you, That I do believe, that from the firſt Inſtitutions of Parliaments, to this hour, there was never a Houſe of Commons fuller of Affection and Duty to their King, then you are to Me; never any that was more deſirous and ſollicitous to gratifie their King, then you are to oblige Me; never a Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179355:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->in which there were fewer perſons without a full meaſure of Zeal, for the Honour and Welfare of the King and Countrie, then there are in this: The wonderfull alacritie that you ſhewed at your firſt coming together, in giving Me ſo liberal a ſupply, was an unqueſtionable inſtance of this; and I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, made Our neighbors abroad look upon Me and you with much the more reſpect and eſteem; and I am perſwaded, even broke the heart of ſome deſperate and ſeditious Deſigns at home. In a word, I know moſt of your faces and names, and can never hope to finde better men in your places.</p>
            <p>You will wonder now, after I have willingly made this juſt acknowledgement to you, that I ſhould lament and even complain, that I and you and the Kingdom, are yet without that preſent fruit and advantage, which We might reaſonably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Our ſelves from ſuch a harmonie of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and a unity in Reſolutions, to advance the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service, and to provide for the Peace and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Kingdom, that you do not expedite thoſe good Councels which are moſt neceſſarie for both.</p>
            <p>I know not how it comes to paſs, but for theſe many weeks paſt, even ſince your laſt Adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, private and particular buſineſs have almoſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179355:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->thruſt the conſideration of the Publick out of doors; and in truth, I do not know that you are nearer ſettling My Revenue, then you were at Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs: I am ſure I have communicated My condition to you without reſerve, what I have coming in, and what My neceſſary Disburſments are; and I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly deceived, if whatever you give Me be any otherwiſe given to Me, then to be iſſued out for your own uſe and benefit; truſt Me, it ſhall be ſo, and if you conſider it well, you will finde that you are the richer by what you give, ſince it is all to be laid out, that you may enjoy the reſt in Peace and Security.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I need not put you in minde of the miſerable effects which have attended the wants and neceſſities of the Crown, I need not tell you, that there is a Republical party ſtill in the Kingdom, which hath the courage to promiſe themſelves an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Revolution; and Me thinks, I ſhould as little need to tell you, that the onely way, with Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to diſappoint their hopes, and indeed to reduce them from thoſe extravagant hopes and deſires, is, to let them ſee, that you have ſo provided for the Crown that it hath wherewithall to ſupport it ſelf, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you, which I am ſure is all I deſire, and deſire on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your preſervation: Therefore I do conjure you, by all the profeſſions of affection you have made to Me, by all the kindneſs I know you have for Me,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179355:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->after all your deliberations, betake your ſelves to ſome ſpeedy reſolutions, and ſettle ſuch a real and ſubſtantial Revenue upon Me, as may hold ſome proportion with the neceſſarie expences I am at for the Peace and Benefit, and Honour of the Kingdom, that they who look for troubles at home, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of their wiſhes, and that Our Neighbours abroad, by ſeeing that all is well at home, may have that eſteem and value of Us, as may ſecure the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and Honour of the Nation, and make the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of this Kingdom, and of this City, once more the admiration and envy of the world.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I hear you are very zealous for the Church, and very ſollicitous, and even jealous that there is not expedition enough uſed in that Affair, I thank you for it, ſince I preſume it proceeds from a good root of Piety and Devotion; but I muſt tell you, I have the worſt luck in the world, if, after all the reproaches of being a Papiſt whilſt I was abroad, I am ſuſpected of being a Presbyterian now I am come home: I know you will not take it unkindly, if I tell you, that I am as zealous for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as any of you can be, and am enough ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the enemies of it, on all ſides; that I am as much in love with the Book of Common Prayer, as you can wiſh, and have prejudice enough to thoſe who do not love it; who I hope in time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179355:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->will be better informed and change their mindes; and you may be confident, I do as much deſire to ſee a Uniformitie ſetl'd, as any amongſt you. I pray truſt Me in that Affair, I promiſe you to haſten the diſpatch of it with all convenient ſpeed, you may relie upon Me in it.</p>
            <p>I have tranſmitted the Book of Common Prayer with thoſe Alterations and Additions, which have been preſented to Me by the Convocation, to the Houſe of Peers, with My Approbation, that the Act of Uniformitie may relate to it; ſo that I preſume it will be ſhortlie diſpatched there: And when We have done all We can, the well-ſetling that Affair will require great Prudence and Diſcretion, and the abſence of all Paſſion and Precipitation.</p>
            <p>I will conclude, with putting you in minde, That the ſeaſon of the Year, the convenience of your being in the countrie, in many reſpects, for the good and welfare of it; for you will finde much Tares have been ſowed there in your abſence; the arrivall of My Wife, who I expect ſome time this Moneth, and the neceſſitie of My own being out of town to meet Her, and to ſtay ſome time before She comes hither, makes it very neceſſarie that the Parliament be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed before Eaſter, to meet again in the Winter: And that it may do ſo, I pray lay aſide private bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, that you may in that time diſpatch the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179355:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->and there are few things I reckon more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick then your providing for the Securitie of the Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, which I have ſo often recommended to you, and do it now very earneſtlie. I pray let no private Animoſities or Conteſts, indanger a work of ſo great a Benefit and Honour to the Nation; but firſt provide for the ſupport of the Work, and then let Juſtice be done for determination of particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <p>The mention of My Wives arrival, puts Me in minde to deſire you to put that Complement upon Her, that Her entrance into the Town may be with more decencie then the ways will now ſuffer it to be: And to that purpoſe, I pray you would quickly paſs ſuch Laws as are before you, in order to the amending thoſe Ways, and that She may not finde <hi>Whitehall</hi> ſurrounded with water.</p>
            <p>I will detain you no longer, but do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe My Self great Fruits of this converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with you, and that you will juſtifie the Confidence I have in your Affections, by letting the world ſee that you take My Concernments to heart, and are ready to do whatſoever I deſire for the Peace and VVelfare of the Kingdom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179355:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
